<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: rfid | Tom Wardill]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.howrandom.net/blog/categories/rfid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.howrandom.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-21T14:50:15+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.howrandom.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tom Wardill]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Touchatag on OSX with tagEventor]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.howrandom.net/blog/2012/09/08/touchatag-on-osx-with-tageventor/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-08T10:58:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.howrandom.net/blog/2012/09/08/touchatag-on-osx-with-tageventor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m planning a talk on monitoring things that aren&rsquo;t servers. The physical realm is something we all interact with, but very rarely actually monitor.</p>

<p>Part of this involves a touchatag (tikitag) RFID reader, my laptop and an Oyster card.</p>

<p>The easiest way to do &lsquo;if this card turns up, do this&rsquo; is some software called <a href="http://code.google.com/p/tageventor/">tagEventor</a>. A simple daemon that listen to the card, and will run a given script for a particular card.</p>

<p>Herein lies instructions on how to make it work on OSX (Mountain Lion in my case, but instructions should apply to most).</p>

<h2>PCSCD</h2>

<p>This is the system daemon for talking to card readers. It&rsquo;s shipped with OSX and has the required dependencies. It needs a modification to the config to work with the Touchatag (as it ships with an unrecognised firmware).</p>

<pre><code>sudo vim /usr/libexec/SmartCardServices/drivers/ifd-ccid.bundle/Contents/Info.plist

Change 
&lt;key&gt;ifdDriverOptions&lt;/key&gt;
&lt;string&gt;0x0000&lt;/string&gt;

to

&lt;key&gt;ifdDriverOptions&lt;/key&gt;
&lt;string&gt;0x0004&lt;/string&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>And either restart the system or run the daemon manually with</p>

<pre><code>sudo /usr/sbin/pcscd -f
</code></pre>

<h2>tagEventor</h2>

<p>Currently, the easiest way to get this is to build it from source, using <a href="https://github.com/bettse/tagEventor">this github branch from bettse</a>.</p>

<p>You will need XCode installed, as it&rsquo;s structured as an XCode project.</p>

<ol>
<li>Clone the branch from github</li>
<li>Open the XCode project</li>
<li>Product > Build</li>
<li>In the left column in XCode, dropdown &lsquo;Products&rsquo;, right click tagEventor and select &lsquo;Show in Finder&rsquo;</li>
<li>Copy the tagEventor binary to somewhere useful</li>
<li>In a terminal, cd to where you put the binary, and run <code>./tagEvent -v 3</code></li>
</ol>


<p>If everything is successful, you will see the output of tagEventor scroll by. If you don&rsquo;t, check that pcscd is running, and try testing that with <code>pcsctest</code>.</p>

<p>Once tagEventor is running, poke a rfid card at it (Oyster cards work), and you should see it detect the card and attempt to run a script. Remove the card and you should see similar output.</p>

<p>Create that script in whatever you&rsquo;re favoured language is, and it&rsquo;ll be executed with arguments when the card appears and leaves.</p>

<p>Enjoy your physical computer interface</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
